IBRAHIM SANUSI

Dayton, OH 45449 | 313-400-1750 | sanusijibrahim@gmail.com

HSEQ MANAGER

Highly motivated and self-driven professional with proven record of experience in waste processing, research, and health safety environment and quality (HSEQ) management. Excellent communication and interpersonal skills with the ability to effectively engage at all level with employees, cross-functional team and management to achieve all business objectives.

Skills and Competencies

- Administrative Documentation
- Continuous Improvement
- Job Hazard Analysis (JHA)
- Management of Change (MOC)
- Presentation (MS PowerPoint)
- Audit (Safety, KPIs, Metrics)
- Microsoft (Excel, Outlook, PowerPoint)
- Training Content Development
- Emergency Preparedness and Response
- Planned Inspection and Maintenance
- Data Visualization (R, Tableau, Power BI)
- Process Safety Management (PSM)
- Data Analysis (R, SAS, SQL, Python, SPSS, Minitab)
- Lean Six Sigma (DMAIC, 5S, TPM, SPC, DOE)
- Regulatory Compliance (OSHA, CFR, DOT, EPA)
- Accident Investigation (Root Cause, FTA, 5 Why's)
- Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs)
- Promotion and Communication of HSE Matters

EDUCATION

Master of Science, Chemical and Biomedical Engineering | Miami University – Oxford, Ohio

01/2019 - 08/2021

Graduate Research thesis link: http://rave.ohiolink.edu/etdc/view?acc_num=miami1626637854831713

Graduate Certificate, Applied Statistics | Miami University – Oxford, Ohio

01/2019 - 08/2021

- Utilized SQL, R, R Shiny, SPSS, SAS, Python, Excel and Minitab for data analysis and visualization.
- Contributed to National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health (NIOSH) Pocket Guide Data Visualization Tool

Bachelor of Engineering, Chemical Engineering | Ahmadu Bello University - Zaria, Nigeria

03/2008 - 10/2012

- First Place, Nigerian Society of Chemical Engineers, Senior Process Design Competition in Nigerian Universities
- Undergraduate Research publication link: http://lejpt.academicdirect.org/A26/065 078.pdf

LICENSES AND CERTIFICATIONS

Certified Safety Professional Board of Certified Safety Professionals	07/2018 – 12/2023
Certified Six Sigma Black Belt American Society for Quality	07/2019 – 12/2022
Certified Associate in Project Management Project Management Institute	07/2019 - 07/2024
Class 2 Wastewater Treatment Professional Operator License Ohio EPA	01/2021 – 12/2023

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research and Teaching Assistant | Miami University - Oxford, Ohio

01/2019 - 08/2021

Conducted a U.S. EPA funded research titled: "Synthesis, Characterization, and Analysis of TiO₂/ZnO Composites Thin Films Photocatalysts for Ethanol Vapor Oxidation" to reduce diurnal evaporative emission in automobile. Formulated, synthesized and characterized semiconductor thin film photocatalysts for photocatalytic activity. Led senior's unit operation laboratory on diffusion, reaction kinetics, process control, and distillations.

Attained 100% oxidation of ethanol and up to 96% degradation of total volatile organic compounds (VOCs).

Health Safety Environment and Quality Manager | S. A. Oladiti and Sons Nigeria Limited

09/2014 – 12/2018

Coordinated haulage activities of petroleum products with about 400 trucks. Developed, implemented, managed and sustained these Total Energies 13 elements International Small Site Safety Rating System (ISSSRS) for loss control: 1) Leadership and Administration, 2) Employees Training and Certification, 3) Emergency Preparedness and Response, 4) Critical Task Analysis, 5) Planned Inspection and Maintenance, 6) Promotion and Communication of HSE Matters, 7) Management Training. 8) Event Notification and Investigation, 9) Organizational Rules/Data/Control of Operations, 10) Procurement of Equipment, 11) Health and Environmental Control, 12) Engineering and Management of Change (MOC), and 13) System Evaluation and Improvement. Managed low capital project, regulation watch, and PPE usage. Conducted quarterly and yearly audit to track key performance indicators (KPIs). Led accident/incident/noncompliance/near-misses investigation to identify the root causes. Followed up on all action plans resulting from audits and investigations and ensure gaps closure to prevent reoccurrence. Established annual HSEQ goals. Maintained operation database, and analyzed and generated monthly report for management decision.

- Raised safety management system (SMS) audit score from 32% to 87% in 2 years. Reduced accident rate by 90%.
- Initiated lean six sigma methodologies to improve truck availability for loading by 50%.